International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Canel Lodge 700 Records 1984.0024
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Canel Lodge 700 Records
undated, 1958 - 1981, 2008
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0024
11 Linear Feet
The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers (IAMAW), Canel Lodge 700 was founded on 20 April 1959. The lodge, located in Middletown, Connecticut, was organized by machinists at the Canel Atomic Testing Lab. In 1959, the local gained collective bargaining recognition from the Canel Lab. Pratt and Whitney took over the plant circa 1965. Pratt and Whitney continued union recognition after the takeover.
Access
The collection is open and available for research with the exception of Series II and Series III individual grievance materials.
Acquisition Information
The materials were deposited in the Connecticut Labor Archives on 14 February 1984, by President Clifford Forster.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative Files, (undated, circa 1961-1981, 2008) consist of minutes of the Executive Board and Delegates meeting from 1971-1975, union listings, employee service records, and flyers. The employee service records [RESTRICTED] are computer-printed listings of active employees, provided monthly by the company to the union as stipulated by the union contract. They are listed alphabetically by name of employee, by clock number, or by department number. The records provide important data on the production workforce, including race, sex, employment and promotion dates, pay grades, etc. The more recent years note union membership. Archives staff took one month (December) sample per year. The items from 2008 consist of "Machinists for Obama" election ephemera.
Series II: Arbitration Cases, (1958-1977) is arranged in two subseries, Lodge 700 and Other Lodges. Lodge 700 records include general grievance material arranged alphabetically by type, and specific grievances arranged alphabetically by name [RESTRICTED].
Series III: National Labor Relations Board Cases, (1958-circa 1981) contain general administrative materials arranged alphabetically, as well as individual case records arranged by case number [RESTRICTED].
History
The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Canel Lodge 700 was founded on 20 April 1959. The lodge, located in Middletown, Connecticut, was organized by machinists at the Canel Atomic Testing Lab. In 1959, the local gained collective bargaining from the Canel Lab. Pratt and Whitney took over the plant about 1965. Pratt and Whitney continued union recognition after their takeover.
Scope and Content
The Canel Lodge records, arranged in three series and cover the years from 1958-1981 and 2008, include minutes, employee, arbitration and administrative records.
Clippings in the scrapbook were taped to the pages in general chronological order. Most of the clippings were dated and had the newspaper source identified. Some clippings were not identified in any way. The tape had dried and fallen off. All clippings were loose and many had been mixed up. It was not in usable condition. The first three pages, with glued clippings, have been left intact. Clippings from the rest of the pages were removed of they had not already fallen off. The clippings were then arranged in chronological order and placed in acid free folders for preservation purposes and to facilitate use.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Photocopies of general labor songs (one copy also remains in the collection) Dodd Call No.
Connecticut State Labor Council, Legislative Bulletins (Several copies)
Machinist Non-Partisan Political League, Action 1975-1977 (3 folders)
International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Report from Headquarters 1975-1977 (3 folders)
United Auto Workers, Solidarity 1969 (2 issues)
Grievance procedures; Connecticut (state); Severance pay; Overtime; Arbitration, Industrial; Machinists; Middletown (inhabited place); Aircraft industry; Aircraft industry workers; Labor; Laboratories; Financial Records; Science; Administrative records; Labor unions; Publications (documents); Nuclear energy; Holiday pay; Wages; Fliers (printed matter); Correspondence; Employees; United Aircraft Corporation. Pratt & Whitney Aircraft Division; Pratt & Whitney Aircraft Group; Canel Atomic Testing Lab
- Series I: Administrative Files, undated, circa 1961 - 1981
  - Minutes: Executive Board and Delegates Meetings, 1971-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 1-5)
  - Union Listings, 1961-1977 (Box 1:, Folder 6-18)
  - RESTRICTED, 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - RESTRICTED, 1964-1981 (Box 1:, Folder 20-37)
  - Job Code Survey, 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - Flyers, undated, 1967-1978 (Box 1:, Folder 39-44)
  - "700 Compass", 1975-1978 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
  - Scrapbook, 1961-1966
  - "Machinists for Obama" election ephemera, 2008 (Box 1:, Folder 107)
- Series II: Arbitration Cases, 1958 - 1977
  - Subseries A: Lodge 700, 1958 - 1976
    - Correspondence, general, [1973], 1976 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - Bulletin board notice grievance, 1974 (Box 2:, Folder 47)
    - Certification of representatives grievance, 1958 (Box 2:, Folder 48)
    - Discharge of Stewards grievance, 1966 (Box 2:, Folder 49)
    - Hourly-job plan grievance, [197?] (Box 2:, Folder 50)
    - Order to show cause to arbitrate: Civil Action No. 13, 760, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 51)
    - Termination for soliciting grievance, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 52)
    - Unemployment compensation grievance, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 53)
    - Wage price freeze grievance, 1972 (Box 2:, Folder 54)
    - RESTRICTED (Box 2:, Folder 55-69)
  - Subseries B: Other Lodges, 1968 - 1975
    - Discharge and suspension: Lodge 743, 1974 (Box 2:, Folder 70)
    - Grievance Procedure: Lodge 1746, 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 71)
    - Holiday Pay: Lodge 743, 1974 (Box 2:, Folder 72)
    - Holiday Pay: Lodge 1746, 1971 (Box 2:, Folder 73)
    - Misuse of working time: Lodge 1746, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 74)
    - Overtime: Lodge 743, 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 75)
    - Overtime and Lay-off: Lodge 743, 1973 (Box 2:, Folder 76)
    - Termination: Lodge 743, 1975 (Box 2:, Folder 77)
    - Termination: Lodge 1746, 1968-1970 (Box 2:, Folder 78)
- Series III: National Labor Relations Board Cases, 1958 - 1981
  - Correspondence, 1958-1977 (Box 2:, Folder 79)
  - "Collyer Policy", 1974, 1977 (Box 2:, Folder 80)
  - Federal court stipulation, 1964-1966 (Box 2:, Folder 81)
  - Withdraw cases and check off, 1968-1981 (Box 2:, Folder 82)
  - "Best" strike decision, 1960-1975 (Box 2:, Folder 83-84)
  - RESTRICTED (Box 2:, Folder 85-106)